Vintage Equipment Collection RG.011
Poly Archives & Special Collections at Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology
Guide to the Vintage Equipment Collection
Early-mid 20th century
RG.011
Poly Archives & Special Collections at Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology
12.0 Cubic feet 13 items
The items in this collection relate to the fields of electrical and civil engineering, as well as supplemental equipment, and were used by engineers in the early to mid 20th century.
Biographical/Historical note
The items in this collection were transferred to the Poly Archives by various university departments. The most prominently represented departments include Civil Engineering and Electrical Engineering.
Scope and Contents note
Equipment in this collection includes items civil and electrical engineers would have used in the early to mid 20th century. Surveying equipment, such as a theodolite and transit, as well as electrical engineering instruments, such as a decade capacitor, decade resistor, potentiometer, and volt meter are included. The equipment ranges in date from the early to mid 20th century.
Arrangement note
Items in this collection are arranged alphabetically.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is currently on display in the Bern Dibner Reading Room of the Bern Dibner Library of Science & Technology.
Please contact the archives to view items in this collection.
Brownie camera; Civil engineering; Electrical engineering; Engineering; Equipment and supplies; Kodak camera; Radio--Equipment and supplies; Surveying
- Book Binding Stapler: Acme Stapling Co., Camden, NJ, undated (Object 1)
  Biographical/Historical note
  This heavy-duty stapler was used to bind the pages of manuals and textbooks.
- Current Transformer: Astra Corporation, Quincy, MA, undated (Object 2)
  A transformer is a piece of equipment used by electrical engineers to test electrical current. If the current in the circuit is too high for a direct measurement, the current transformer is used to produce a reduced current proportional to the current in the circuit.
- Decade Capacitor, Series 1575: Cornell-Dubilier Electronics Inc., Plainfield, NJ, circa 1940 (Object 3)
  A decade capacitor is used for testing and calibration of electrical equipment
- Decade Condenser Type 219-K: General Radio Co., Cambridge, MA, circa 1950 (Object 4)
  The condenser was used when a resistor of unknown or precise value is needed. Condensers are now referred to as capacitors.
- Decade Resistor Type 1432-K: General Radio Co., Cambridge, MA, circa 1950 (Object 5)
  The resistor box contains resistors of many values with mechanical switches to allow precision switching from one value to another. This configuration offers a convenient way of quickly changing resistance in a laboratory setting.
- Electrical Cables: Consolidated Edison Co., New York, NY, undated; These cables were removed from the display when it was discovered they were leaking a viscous fluid. They were bagged and returned to the archives. (Object 6)
  NYU-Poly and Con Edison have a long-standing relationship of mutual research and support. Con Ed was one of NYU-Poly’s first neighbors in the new MetroTech Center complex. These electrical cables and components were donated from Con Ed to NYU-Poly.
  Note on cable reads, "Piece of cable installed in Morgan Stanley building, that failed."
- Gauge: Airco, New York, NY, undated (Object 7)
  This gauge was used to measure the pressure of various gases.
- Hawkeye Brownie Camera: Eastman Kodak, Rochester, NY, circa 1950 (Object 8)
  The Hawkeye was one of the most popular Brownie cameras made. It was cheap, easy to use, and disassembled easily for cleaning: the perfect camera to take into the field.
- Potentiometer: Leeds and Northrup Co., Philadelphia, PA, circa 1950 (Object 9)
  This instrument is a voltage divider used for measuring electric potential.
- Theodolite: Buff & Buff Mfg. Co., Boston, MA, undated (Object 10)
  The theodolite is an optical surveying instrument used by civil engineers to measure angles in vertical and horizontal planes. When the telescope is pointed at an object, the angle of orientation can be measured with precision.
- Transit: Buff & Buff Mfg. Co., Boston, MA, undated (Object 11)
  A transit is a type of theodolite. Rather than being closed, the transit has an open design where measurements are made by reading verniers on metal circles. This transit, produced by the Buff & Buff Company, is often referred to as a Buffmaster Transit.
- Volt Meter, Model 377: Simpson Electrical Co., Chicago, IL, circa 1950 (Object 12)
  This instrument is used to measure the electrical potential difference between two points in an electric circuit.
- Wheatstone Bridge: Leeds and Northrup Co., Philadelphia, PA, undated (Object 13)
  The Wheatstone bridge is a type of potentiometer that measures electrical resistance by balancing two legs of a bridge circuit.